Guide to the Rice University Department of Fine Arts records, John O'Neil, Chairman, 1960-1969 UA 036
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Rice University Department of Fine Arts records, John O'Neil, Chairman
1960-1969
1965-1968
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Rice University. Department of Fine Arts.
UA 036
3.5 Linear Feet (8 boxes)
This collection contains correspondence, memos, budgeting and accounting records, and other materials associated with the operation of the Fine Arts Department of Rice University from 1960-1969. The bulk of the material is from 1965 to 1968.
Biographical / Historical
Rice University's Department of Fine Arts was established as part of Architecture in 1959 and James Chillman acted as the temporary chairman. Mr. William Caudill took over this job in 1961. In the early 1960's the Fine Arts Department (changed to the Department of Art and Art History in 1978) consisted of several courses in drawing, painting, sculpture, and art history. The faculty at that time was made up of Charles Schorre, David Parsons, Katherine Brown, and James Chillman as well as Jasper Rose, an Englishman who taught painting and art history. Eleanor Evans came in 1964 to teach a basic design course for freshmen architects. During that time the department offered neither a degree nor a major in fine arts. It served as a service department for the entire University to provide electives for all students. Sandy Havens, director of the Rice Players, requested he be assigned to the Fine Arts Department instead of the English Department.
At that time the Department was housed in the basement of Fondren Library with studio courses being taught in a temporary metal building at the base of the track stadium. In 1968, the Department moved to Allen Center where the first art gallery was established. During the first years, important exhibits included drawings of Dorothy Hood and photographs of Geoff Winningham. It was decided to begin building a permanent collection. The department moved to their new quarters in Sewall Hall in the early 1970's. There they had classrooms, studios and offices.
In 1969 Dominique and John de Menil left the sponsorship of the Art History Department and gallery at the University of St. Thomas and proposed moving these activities to Rice University. The move of the entire Art Department, collection and staff, was completed and the de Menil's Institute for the Arts at Rice was born. The Institute sponsored exhibits and published catalogs of national and international interest.
In 1965 John O'Neil was asked to become Chairman of the Department of Fine Arts. He accepted on the basis of being 'acting' chairman since it was not certain what the situation would be. In 1967 he decided to accept a permanent appointment at Rice. When the de Menil merger was completed, he continued as Chairman and Mrs. de Menil was the director of the Institute for the Arts.
In 1965 a proposal was made for an undergraduate major in Fine Arts at Rice University. In the 1970's and 1980's a Master of Arts degree in history of art and 5th year bachelors degree in studio were offered.
Parts excerpted from "The Cornerstone," published by the Rice Historical Society, Winter/Spring 2001. Also see History of Fine Arts, File 7.8
Scope and Contents
This collection contains correspondence, memos, budgeting and accounting records, and other materials associated with the operation of the Fine Arts Department of Rice University from 1960-1969. The bulk of the material is from 1965 to 1968. Additional records include materials associated with the operation and promotion of the Allen Center gallery. Most of the papers are from the years when John O'Neil was active in the department. Some early papers are from Bill Lacy, associate chairman, and William Caudill, chairman of the Architecture Department. This collection offers a look at how Rice University created the Fine Arts Department that eventually led Dominique and John de Menil to transfer their patronage from the University of St. Thomas to Rice in 1969.
Restrictions on Access
This material is open for research. Stored off-site at the Library Service Center. Please request this material via woodson@rice.edu or call 713-348-2586.
Acquisition Information
On November 21, 2002, Geraldine Aramanda, the archivist with the Menil Museum, gave these papers on behalf of the Menil to Rice University.
Related Materials
See also information files for Fine Arts Department and Art and Art History Department and John O'Neil.
Accruals
No future additions are expected for this material.
Index Terms
Subjects
Universities and colleges
Document Types
financial records; documents; corrrespondence
Subjects (Persons)
O'Neil, John
Subjects (Corporations)
Rice University. Department of Art History.
- Series I: Administrative Files, 1962-1968; 226495
  Scope and Contents note
  Included are budget and accounting papers, University policy memos, faculty travel and flood insurance correspondence and claims generated from a flood in the basement of Fondren Library on May 13, 1966 that damaged artwork from applicants for a faculty position. Some salary information for faculty may be found in the budget files. Budget for library purchases is in this series.
  - Accounting Memos, 1965-1968; 226508 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Accounting Policies - Fine Arts Department, 1965; 226507 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Budget, Current, 1965-1966; 226506 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Budget, Current, 1966-1967; 226505 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Budget, Current, 1967-1968; 226504 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Budget, Request, 1965-1966; 226503 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Budget, Request, 1966-1967; 226502 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Budget, Request, 1967-1968; 226501 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Budget-Library, 1967-1968; 226500 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Flood Insurance, 1966-1967; 226499 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Policies - Dr. Pitzer, 1962-1968; 226498 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Policies - General, 1965-1968; 226497 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Travel - Faculty, 1964-1968; 226496 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Series II: Committees - On and Off Campus, 1965-1968; 226488
  Series II contains correspondence and in a few cases, minutes, from various on and off campus committees and organizations.
  - Advisory Councils, 1967; 226494 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Committees - Miscellaneous, 1965-1968; 226493 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Cultural Affairs Committee, 1968; 226492 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Committee on Examinations and Standing, 1966-1967; 226491 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Committee on Humanities Research, 1966; 226490 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Committee on Public Lectures, 1966-1968; 226489 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Series III: Courses and Enrollment, 1965-1969; 226478
  Series III contains documents pertaining to the art and art history courses offered, enrollment, and schedules. There is also correspondence relating to the proposal of a Fine Arts Major at Rice University. Also there are lists of students accepted as majors. Grading and examination schedules, etc., are also included.
  - Course Enrollment, 1965-1968; 226487 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Course Schedules, 1966-1967; 226486 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Course Schedules, 1967-1968; 226485 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Course Enrollment, 1965-1967; 226484 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Course Offered, 1967-1968; 226483 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Course Offered, 1968-1969; 226482 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Fine Arts, Majors, 1966-1968; 226481 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Fine Arts, Proposal, 1965; 226480 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Grading and Examination Schedule, 1965-1968; 226479 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Series IV: Exhibits and Gallery Information, 1960-1969; 226449
  Series IV contains material from art department exhibits and gallery information. The exhibits are listed by artist name. There are gallery exhibits and transient exhibitions. These files may include press releases, brochures and announcements sent out to the community. Some of the general files pertain to artwork gifts and the CAA collection. There is also a folder of membership information such as MOMA, College Art Association, American Educational Theatre Association, Print Council of America, etc. Policies for operation of the gallery are included as well as a brief outline of the opening of the Allen Center Gallery and the plans for its operation.
  - Acquisitions Advisory Committee - Artwork gift for Rice University, 1967; 226477 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Thomas Bang Sculpture, 1967-1968; 226476 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - CAA Collection/Rice, 1960-1968; 226475 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - College Art Association of America, 1965-1968; 226474 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - DeKuffner, Tamara Donation, n.d.; 226473 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Exhibitions, 1965-1966; 226472 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Exhibitions, 1966-1967; 226471 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Exhibitions - Fine Arts Gallery, 1967-1969; 226470 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Exhibitions/Transient - American Federation of Art, 1967-1968; 226469 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Exhibitions/Transient - Museum of Modern Art, 1966-1968; 226468 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Exhibitions/Transient - Museum of Modern Art, 1968-1969; 226467 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Fine Arts Exhibit, 1964-1965; 226466 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Fine Arts Gallery, 1967; 226465 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Gallery Exhibitions - American Printmakers: The Avant Garde, 1967-1968; 226464 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Gallery Exhibitions - Thomas Bang Sculpture, 1968-1969; 226463 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Gallery Exhibitions - The British Eye Prints, 1968; 226462 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Gallery Exhibitions - Bob Camblin, 1967-1968; 226461 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Gallery Exhibitions - Dorothy Hood, 1969; 226460 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Gallery Exhibitions - Ferdinand Rotan Galleries, Inc., 1968; 226459 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Gallery Exhibitions - Daniel Shapiro, 1967-1968; 226458 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Gallery Exhibitions - Oli Sihvonen, 1967; 226457 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Gallery Exhibitions - John Thomas Paintings, 1968; 226456 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Gallery Exhibitions - Winningham/Johnson, 1968; 226455 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Gallery Policies, 1967; 226454 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Memberships, 1965-1968; 226453 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Press Releases, 1967-1968; 226452 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Tony Smith Exhibition, 1969; 226451 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Earl Staley, One Man Show, 1967; 226450 (Box 5, Folder 12)
- Series V: General Business and Correspondence, 1961-1968; 226419
  Series V contains the general files such as calendars, correspondence and other general business of the Fine Arts Department. Much of the correspondence is between the chairman and other university offices, such as Dean of Humanities, faculty, and other campus departments. There is one folder of John O'Neil's personal correspondence and includes a photograph of him. Some of the general information pertains to students and a couple of folders pertain to foreign study. There is correspondence about the publishing of a student magazine called "Collage." Fellowship and scholarship information is found in this series. One file contains correspondence relating to the Fine Arts Studio Building near the old stadium. One architectural drawing is included. There is a brief history of the department's early days.
  - Calendar, 1965-1967; 226448 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Calendar - Fine Arts, 1966-1967; 226447 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence - Campus Departments, 1966-1968; 226446 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence - Dean of Humanities, 1965-1968; 226445 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence - Drama, 1966; 226444 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence - Faculty, 1965-1968; 226443 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence - Fine Arts, 1961-1964; 226442 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence - Fine Arts, 1964-1965; 226441 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence - Fine Arts, 1965-1968, 226440 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence - Fine Arts Studio, 1965-1967, 226439 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence - Miscellaneous, 1967-1968; 226438 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence - John O'Neil, Memos, 1967; 226437 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence - John O'Neil, Miscellaneous, 1965-1967; 226436 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence - John O'Neil, Miscellaneous, 1968; 226435 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence - John O'Neil, Personal, 1965-1967; 226434 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Faculty Meeting Minutes, 1965; 226433 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Fellowships and Scholarships, 1965-1967; 226432 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Films, Lost Claim (Hepworth and American Folk Art), 1968; 226431 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Fine Arts in Texas Research Project, 1967; 226430 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Foreign Proposals, 1965-1966; 226429 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Graduate Student Information, 1956-1968; 226428 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Guadalajara Summer Session, 1966-1967; 226427 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - History of Fine Arts Department, 226426 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Houston Arts Festival, 1967; 226425 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Lecturers - John O'Neil, 1968; 226424 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Rice University Review, 1966-1967; 226423 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Student-Related Information, General, 1964-1968; 226422 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Student Journal, Collage, 1966; 226421 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Thresher, General Course Review, 1966; 226420 (Box 7, Folder 14)
- Series VI: Personnel, 1962-1969; 226400
  Series VI contains the personnel files from the Fine Arts Department. Files on some visiting lecturers and some resumes and correspondence are included here. The then current staff member's curriculum vitae files are included. One file is from President Pitzer's office and pertains to Fine Arts candidates for employment. The Miscellaneous Correspondence file includes some personnel correspondence that has references to hiring decisions and other departmental milestones such as the gallery program.
  - Alahadeff, Albert, History of Art, 1968; 226418 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Alloway, Lawrence, Visiting Lecturer, 1966-1967; 226417 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Bang, Thomas, Studio, 1967-1969; 226416 (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Baumann, Edzard, Art History (Declined), 1965; 226415 (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - Begley, Wayne, Art History, 1966-1968; 226414 (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - Belz, Carl, Art History (Declined), 1968; 226413 (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - Caldwell, Martha, Art History, 1966-1967; 226412 (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - Fridge, Roy, Special Projects, 1968-1969; 226411 (Box 7, Folder 22)
  - Kane, William M., Art History, 1965; 226410 (Box 7, Folder 23)
  - Kung, David S., Lecturer, 1965-1966, 226409 (Box 7, Folder 24)
  - Mears, Herbert, Studio, 1965-1966; 226408 (Box 7, Folder 25)
  - Rose, Jasper, Art History, 1964-1965; 226407 (Box 7, Folder 26)
  - Staley, Earl V., Studio, 1966-1969; 226406 (Box 7, Folder 27)
  - Candidates - Fine Arts (from President's Office), 1962-1965; 226405 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Personnel - Curriculum Vitae, 1966-1967; 226404 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Personnel - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1963-1969; 226403 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Personnel - Recommendations, John O'Neil, 1965-1967; 226402 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Visiting Lecturers, 1964-1968; 226401 (Box 8, Folder 5)